Guide to the Missoula Business and Professional Women Records 1920-1996 (bulk 1923-1988)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Missoula Business and Professional Women records
1920-1996 (bulk 1923-1988)
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 836
Missoula Business and Professional Women
5.1 linear feet
The Missoula Business and Professional Women is an organization in Missoula, Montana that promotes equal rights for women in the workplace. This collection primarily consists of reports, minutes, and correspondence generated by the operation of the organization and programs from the annual state conventions.
Historical Note
The National Federation of Business and Professional Women’s Clubs organized in 1919 for the purpose of unifying American working women and providing them a means to work toward equality in their professions. In the state of Montana, Missoula was the first city to initiate any local activity and organized a state meeting in March 1921. Missoula resident Lillian Payne acted as the organizer and chair of the first meeting. The state held its first convention in Missoula in 1922 and the city was well represented with residents Amelia Loffnes elected Director, Mabel Humphrey Treasurer, and Elizabeth Powell National Vice President.
Missoula’s organization held a prominent place in the state club, with members repeatedly serving as directors and state officers. The Missoula chapter actively participated in state club activities including: the Young Career Woman contest that recognized young, female professionals; the Woman of Achievement/Woman of the Year Award; and numerous scholarship programs. In more recent years, Missoula members have been crucially active in the Silent Witness Initiative in Montana a project devoted to raising awareness about domestic violence. The club continued in its tradition of serving Missoula women through disseminating information, informed advocacy, and educating the public on issues pertaining to women’s rights.
This collection is primarily materials related to the operation and maintenance of the Missoula Business and Professional Women organization including meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, clippings, financial information, membership lists, photographs, applications, scholarship information, constitutions, yearbooks, and scrapbook pages. There is also material pertaining to the Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women’s Clubs including annual convention programs, emblem ceremony programs, and pamphlets. It also contains programs and reports on the meetings of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs as well as publications and mailings from the organization. There are also materials relating to the International Federation of Business and Professional Women’s Clubs including publications and pamphlets.
The collection is arranged into four series with folders arranged chronologically or alphabetically.
Series I: Missoula Business and Professional Women and Other Montana Chapters, 1920-1996
Series II: National and International Business and Professional Women’s Clubs, 1923-1983 and undated
Series III: Photographs and Negatives, 1935-1957 and undated
Series IV: Memorabilia, 1934-1957
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
This collection was donated by Vickie Amundson on May 13, 2004.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Missoula Business and Professional Women--Archives; Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs; National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs; International Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs
Businesswomen--Montana--Missoula; Women in the professions--Montana--Missoula--Societies and clubs; Women--Montana--Missoula--Societies and clubs
Photographs
Women; Missoula
- Missoula Business and Professional Women and Other Montana Chapters, 1920-1996 and undated; Series I.; 3.9 linear feet
  These materials document the operating procedures of the Missoula Business and Professional Women and contain materials relating to Montana state conventions and other chapters of the Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs.
  - Certificate of Membership in National Federation, July 15, 1920 (Box-folder 7/11)
  - Meeting Minutes, Missoula, 1920-1930 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Receipts, Missoula, 1922-1938 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Reports, Missoula, 1923-1940 and undated (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Membership, Missoula, 1923-1941 and undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Operations, Missoula, 1923-1989 and undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1924 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Constitutions, Missoula, 1929 and undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1929-1940 and undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1930 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Year Book, Glendive, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Transportation Committee, Missoula, 1930-1934 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Year Books, Missoula, 1930-1986 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1931 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Officer's Reports, Missoula, 1931-1939 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - President's Reports, Missoula, 1931-1940 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Meeting Minutes, Missoula, 1931-1946 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Scholarships, Missoula, 1931-1977 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - History of the Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1931-1988 and undated (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Clippings, 1931-1996 and undated (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Finance Committee, Missoula, 1932-1941 and undated (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Ledger, Missoula, 1933-1947 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Program, Great Falls, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Savings Account, Missoula, 1935-1941 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Montana Business Woman, Publication, 1935-1982 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1936 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Surveys, 1936 and undated (Box-folder 2/14)
  - District Meeting Minutes, Butte, 1939 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Meeting Minutes, Missoula, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Correspondence, Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Membership Applications, Missoula, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Radio Script for Business Women's Week, Missoula, October 1944 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Reports, Missoula, 1945-1949 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Executive Board Meeting, Missoula, July 1947 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Correspondence, Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1947-1984 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Programs, Missoula, 1948-1966 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Sponsoring Citation Award, Missoula, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1951 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Statement of Club Membership, Missoula, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1952 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1953 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1954 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1956 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1957 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Civic Participation, Missoula, 1957-1968 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Historical Data, Missoula, July 1960 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1960 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1963 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Emblem Breakfast, Missoula, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Scrapbook, Missoula, 1963-1986 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Montana Annual Conventions, Member Addresses and Telephone Numbers, 1963-1986 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1965 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Meeting Agenda and Resolution, District II, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Radio and Television Release, Missoula, October 22, 1969 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1969 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Status of Women, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary of Missoula Business and Professional Women, 1970 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Montana Member Directory, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Handbook of Procedures, Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, June 1971 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Women of Achievement, Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1971-1978 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1972 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Scrapbook, Missoula, 1972-1975 (Box OS 9)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1973 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Officers and Members, Missoula, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 4/16)
  - The Montana Woman, Publication, 1974-1981 (Box-folder 4/17)
  - Year Book, Helena, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - By-Laws, Butte, 1976 (Box-folder 4/19)
  - Montana Handbook of Procedures, June 1976 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1976 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - District II Spring Conference, April 17, 1977 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Bicentennial, 1977 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Emblem Ceremony, Missoula, 1977 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1977 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Young Career Woman, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Meeting Minutes, Missoula, 1977-1979 and undated (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Reports, District II, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1978 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Montana Equal Rights Council, 1978 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Sponsor in Seminars, Missoula, 1979 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Montana Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs Membership, 1979 (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Emblem Ceremony Booklet and Seals, Missoula, April 19, 1980 (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Montana Leadership/Orientation Seminar, November 1980 (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1980 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Young Career Woman, Intructions for Judges, 1981 (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Mailings, Missoula, 1982 (Box-folder 5/18)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1982 (Box-folder 5/19)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1983 (Box-folder 5/20)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1984 (Box-folder 5/21)
  - National Program Award, 1984 (Box-folder 5/22)
  - Taxes, Missoula, 1984 (Box-folder 5/23)
  - Young Career Woman, Biographical Information Sheets, 1986 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1987 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1988 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Hands-Across-the-Border, 1995 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Montana Annual Convention, 1996 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - "A Collect", undated (Box-folder 6/6)
  - District II Operations, undated (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Goals, undated (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Legislation Survey, District II, undated (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Meeting Minutes, Missoula, undated (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Scrapbook Pages, Missoula, undated (Box-folder 6/11)
- National and International Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1923-1983 and undated; Series II.; 0.5 linear feet
  These materials document some operations and events of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs and International Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs.
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc., 1923-1939 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Report on Tenth Annual National Convention, 1928 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Equality Research, National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1931-1940 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - International Federation of Business and Professional Women, 1931-1968 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Business Women's Week, 1936-1970 and undated (Box-folder 6/16)
  - Song Book, National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1938 (Box-folder 6/17)
  - Publicity, National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs Biennial Convention, 1939 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs Handbook of Federation Procedures, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs Biennial Convention, 1947-1976 and undated (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Pattern for the Business and Professional Woman, 1964 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - National Business Women's Week, 1977 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs Federation-Foundation Report, 1983 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Emblem, Drawing, undated (Box-folder 7/6)
  - "Memo to the Club President," Suggested Orientation Outline, undated (Box-folder 7/7)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs Pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 7/8)
- Photographs, 1935-1957 and undated; Series III.; 0.1 linear feet
  Photographs and negatives relating to the Missoula Business and Professional Women.
  - Photographs, 1957 and undated (Box-folder 7/9)
  - Photograph, Biennial Convention National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Olympia Hotel, Seattle, Washington, July 15, 1935 (Box OS 10)
  - Negatives, undated (Box-folder 7/10)
- Memorabilia, 1934-1957 and undated; Series IV.; 0.6 linear feet
  Artifacts related to the Missoula Business and Professional Women.
  - Montana Annual Convention, Evelyn Skreen Nametag, 1934 (Box 8)
  - Fifteenth Montana Annual Convention Ribbon, 1936 (Box 8)
  - Binennial Convention, Kansas City, Nina Ford Nametag, 1939 (Box 8)
  - Eighteenth Montana Annual Convention Ribbon, 1939 (Box 8)
  - Montana Loves BPW Button, undated (Box 8)
  - Three BPWC Missoula, MT Keychains, 1955 (Box 8)
  - BPW President, Silver Plate, 1956-1957 (Box 8)
  - BPW Board, Silver Plate, 1956-1957 (Box 8)
  - Large Business and Professional Women Emblem Button, undated (Box 8)
  - Small Business and Professional Women Emblem Button, undated (Box 8)